David Soares Batista

Personal Data

PLACE AND DATE OF BIRTH: Lisbon, January 4th, 1981

PHONE: +49 (0)1523 850 98 89 (mobile)

EMAIL: dsbatista@inesc-id.pt

HOMEPAGE: http://davidsbatista.github.io

SUMMARY

I like to explore and extract knowledge from large volumes of data, be it structured or unstructured, numbers or text. I'm experienced in Machine Learning, Natural Language Processing and Big-Data.

In the past I've worked in projects, tackling problems with a strong text-mining and text-analysis components, involving tasks such as information extraction, classification, clustering and information retrieval.

In 2016, I successfully defended my Ph.D., proposing new methods to perform semantic relationship extraction from large collections of documents.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Jan. 2016 - Present

Data Engineer @ HelloFresh AG (http://www.hellofresh.de)

- Text analysis of customer NPS comments with NLP and ML.
- Data Warehousing and processes automation for data analysis.
- $\bullet\,$ Design, build and maintain ETLs and infrastructure for batch processing.
- Technologies: Python NLTK, scikit-learn, Spark, Hive, Impala, Airflow.

 ${\rm Jun.\ 2011-Apr.\ 2014}$

Researcher and Developer @ INESC-ID (http://www.inesc-id.pt)

Project: REACTION - Computational Journalism

- Named Entity Recognition and Disambiguation over news articles.
- \bullet Semantic Relationship Extraction between named-entities.
- Topic Modeling (i.e., LDA) techniques applied to on-line news.
- Analysis of large graphs connecting entities and topics.

Ост. 2009 – Ост. 2011

Researcher and Developer @ LASIGE (http://www.lasige.di.fc.ul.pt)

Project: GREASE - Geographic Reasoning for Search Engines

- Language identification on a web-crawl using n-grams models.
- Disambiguation of geographic ambiguous names in Portuguese text.
- Alignment between geo-ontologies by linking geographical references.

Oct. 2007 - Jul. 2008

Software Developer @ Nokia Siemens Networks

- Development of data collection modules for a GSM monitoring system.
- Technologies: Java, CORBA Architecture, Oracle RDBMS

Computer Skills

Programming: Python, Java, Shell Scripting Machine Learning: scikit-learn, gensim, MinorThird

Natural Language Processing: Python NLTK, Stanford CoreNLP, LingPipe

Distributed Computing: Hadoop, Spark, Hive, Impala

Information Retrieval: Apache Lucene/Solr

Databases/NoSQL: MySQL, PostgreSQL, REDIS

EDUCATION

2011 - 2015

Doctor of Philosphy (Ph.D.) Instituto Superior Técnico, University Lisbon.

"Large-Scale Semantic Relationship Extraction"

To achieve scalable relationship extraction, I proposed using an on-line classifier, based on the idea of nearest neighbor classification, and leveraging min-hash and locality sensitive hashing for efficient similarity search. To obtain training data, for the classifier, I proposed a bootstrapping technique relying on distributional word representations.

2007-2009

Master's Degree (M.Sc.) - Faculty of Sciences, University of Lisbon. "Geographic Text Mining"

I developed an information extraction system based on Conditional Random Fields to generate geographic summaries. The summary lists the geographic entities found in a document and mapped into geographic concepts in a geographic ontology. The system was applied to a crawl of the Portuguese Web (25GB raw text) using a Hadoop cluster.

2003-2007

Bachelor of Science (B.Sc.), Informatics Engineering, Faculty of Sciences, University Lisbon.

2005-2006, Karlsruhe Universität (TH), Germany

• Erasmus exchange student for two semesters

2004 November - 2005 July - IT support (part-time) @ University of Lisbon

 \bullet Troubleshooting network connections and services, preventative maintenance, helping and educating new users.

2003 NOVEMBER - 2004 MARCH - SysAdmin (part-time) @ University of Lisbon

• Administration and configuration of networking software and services (e.g., samba, backups, quotas, mail, web, crontab, IPTables).

LANGUAGES

PORTUGUESE: Native Speaker

English: Spoken: Fluent Written: Fluent

GERMAN: Spoken: Good Written: Fair Certification: Goethe-Zertifikat B.1

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Semi-Supervised Bootstrapping of Relationship Extractors with Distributional Semantics. David S Batista, Bruno Martins, and Mário J Silva. In *Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing-EMNLP'15.* - Honorable Mention for Best Short Paper

A Minwise Hashing Method for Addressing Relationship Extraction from Text. David S Batista, Rui Silva, Bruno Martins, and Mário J Silva. In Web Information Systems Engineering-WISE'13.

Exploring DBpedia and Wikipedia for Portuguese Semantic Relationship Extraction David Soares Batista, David Forte, Rui Silva, Bruno Martins, and Mário J. Silva. *Linguamática*, 5(1), 2013.

Toponym Disambiguation using Ontology-based Semantic Similarity David S Batista, João D Ferreira, Francisco M Couto, and Mário J Silva. In *Computational Processing of the Portuguese Language* 2012.

A Statistical Study of the WPT05 Crawl of the Portuguese Web David Batista and Mário J. Silva. In *In FALA 2010 VI Jornadas en Tecnología del Habla and II Iberian SLTech Workshop* Universidade de Vigo, 2010.

Geographic Signatures for Semantic Retrieval David S Batista, Mário J Silva, Francisco M Couto, and Bibek Behera. In *Proceedings of the 6th Workshop on Geographic Information Retrieval* ACM, 2010.